Guide to the Henry Ashby Turner, Jr. Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Henry Ashby Turner, Jr. papers
1982-2000
MS 1691
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
2 boxes
187
The papers consist of Henry Ashby Turner's correspondence with other historians about the controversy surrounding David Abraham's book, The Collapse of the Weimar Republic. A later accession comprises two databases, one containing information concerning foreign workers in the Adam Opel AG plant in Rüsselsheim, Germany, during the World War II era, and the other containing evaluative records concerning documents and articles relating to General Motors' acquisition, ownership, management, loss of effective control, write-off, and reacquisition of Adam Opel AG during the period from 1929 through the early 1950s.
Turner, Henry Ashby
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Henry Ashby Turner, Jr., 1995 and 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
Biographical / Historical
Henry Ashby Turner, Jr., born in 1932, received his B.A. degree from Washington and Lee University in 1954, and his M.A. (1957) and Ph.D. (1960) from Princeton. He held the following positions at Yale University: instructor in history, 1958-1961; assistant professor, 1962-1964; associate professor, 1964-1970; professor, 1971-1989; Charles Seymour Professor of History, 1990-1991; and Bass Professor of History, 1991-. Turner was master of Davenport College from 1981-1991. He was a noted scholar of modern Europe, particularly Germany. Turner died on December 17, 2008, in New Haven, Connecticut.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of Henry Ashby Turner's correspondence with other historians about the controversy surrounding David Abraham's book, The Collapse of the Weimar Republic. A later accession comprises two databases, one containing information concerning foreign workers in the Adam Opel AG plant in Rüsselsheim, Germany, during the World War II era, and the other containing evaluative records concerning documents and articles relating to General Motors' acquisition, ownership, management, loss of effective control, write-off, and reacquisition of Adam Opel AG during the period from 1929 through the early 1950s.
Automobile industry and trade -- Germany -- History; Historians -- United States; Germany -- History -- 1918-1933; Rüsselsheim (Germany); Turner, Henry Ashby; General Motors Corporation; Opel AG
- Inventory
  - Abraham, David, general correspondence, 1982 - 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Christmas exchange [copies of documents cited in Abraham's work] (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Reusch-Schacht correspondence [copies of documents cited in Abraham's work] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Allen, William Sheridan, 1983, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Historical Association, general correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Perspectives ad, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Perspectives letter, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - American Historical Review letters, 1983 - 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bennett, Edward W., 1983 - 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Berghahn, Volker, 1987 - 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Borchardt, Knut, 1983, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Borg, Daniel, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Brands, Maarten, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Catholic University, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Clifton, James A., 1984 - 1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Craig, Gordon A., 1983 - 1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - European History Quarterly, 1987 - 1988 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Feldman, Gerald D., 1983 - 1986, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Geiss, Imanuel, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Hamilton, Richard F., 1982 - 1985 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Herzog, Bodo, 1982 - 1984 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Himmelfarb, Gertrude, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - James, Harold, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Junker, Detlef, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Köhler, Henning, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Kruger, Peter, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Lang, Serge - "The Nation-Wiener File", undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Lelyveld, Joseph, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Maier, Charles S., 1983 - 1984 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Mason, Timothy W., 1983 - 1985, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Mathews, William, 1985 - 1986 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Mayer, Arno J., 1983 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Mitchell, Allan, 1984 - 1985 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Mommsen, Hans, 1983, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Mommsen, Wolfgang J., 1983 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - The Nation, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Neebe, Reinhard, 1983 - 1984 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - The New York Review of Books, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Nocken, Ulrich, 1983 - 1985 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Pflanze, Otto, 1983 - 1985 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Pravda, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Princeton University, History Deparment, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Princeton University Press, 1983, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Ransel, David L., 1985 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Schoenbaum, David, 1982 - 1985 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Schuker, Stephen A., 1983 - 1985 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Schulz, Gerhard, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Stern, Fritz, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Trexler, Richard C., 1983 - 1984 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Unfug, Douglas, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Vierteljahrshefte für Zeitgeschichte, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Wehler, Hans-Ulrich, 1983 - 1985 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Weinberg, Gerhard L., 1983 - 1985, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Winkler, Heinrich A., 1983 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Woodward, C. Vann, 1984 - 1985 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Miscellaneous letters, 1983 - 1985 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - References to publications - "Published Commentaries on the Abraham Affair", undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Additional material, Circa 1998-circa 2000; Accession 2010-M-040
  Scope and Contents
  This accession comprises two databases, one containing information concerning foreign workers in the Adam Opel AG plant in Rüsselsheim, Germany during the World War II era, and the other containing evaluative records concerning documents and articles relating to General Motors' acquisition, ownership, management, loss of effective control, write-off, and reacquisition of Adam Opel AG during the period from 1929 through the early 1950s. These databases were created sometime betweeen 1998 and 2000 by a team of researchers directed by Professor Henry A. Turner of Yale University.
  Related Archival Materials note
  See also: General Motors Documents Relating to World War II Corporate Activities in Europe (MS 1799). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
  Bibliography
  Related Publication Note: The databases were created during the course of research that resulted in the following publication: Turner, Henry Ashby, Jr. General Motors and the Nazis: The Struggle for Control of Opel, Europe's Biggest Carmaker. New Haven: Yale University Press, 2005.
  - Arbeiter database, Circa 1998-circa 2000; 1 computer file (Microsoft Access)
    This database contains information on foreign workers at the Adam Opel AG plan in Rüsselsheim, Germany, during the early 1930s through World War II. This information was extracted from Ostarbeiter (Eastern worker) savings books and personnel records maintained by Opel.
    Conditions Governing Access
    The computer files are unprocessed and are in a physical state that requires staff intervention before use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu. The staff intervention may take up to 10 business days.
  - Historical documentation database, Circa 1998-circa 2000; 1 computer file (FileMaker)
    This database contains evaluative information regarding significant documents and publications relating to General Motors' acquisition, ownership, management, loss of effective control, write-off, and reacquisition of Adam Opel AG from 1929 through the early 1950s.